<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on lowRISC</title>
    <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on lowRISC</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 09:50:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC 0-6 milestone release</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/11/lowrisc-0-6-milestone-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 09:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/11/lowrisc-0-6-milestone-release/</guid>
      <description>The lowRISC 0.6 milestone release is now available. This release includes an updated version of the Rocket RISC-V core, a higher core clock frequency, JTAG debugging support, Ethernet improvements, and more. See the release notes, for full details. We&amp;rsquo;ve also taken the opportunity to re-organise our documentation, adding an easy to follow quick-start guide.
Our next development focus is to add support for dropping in the Ariane RISC-V design (from ETH Zurich) as an alternative to Rocket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barcelona RISC-V Workshop: Day Two</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/05/barcelona-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/05/barcelona-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</guid>
      <description>The eighth RISC-V workshop is continuing today in Barcleona. As usual, I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Look back here for the day one live blog.
Note that slides from most presentations are now available at riscv.org.
Fast interrupts for RISC-V: Krste Asanovic  Embedded is a major use for RISC-V. There is a desire for faster interrupt handling with support for nested preempted interrupts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barcelona RISC-V Workshop: Day One</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/05/barcelona-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/05/barcelona-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</guid>
      <description>The eighth RISC-V workshop is going on today in Barcleona. As usual, I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Follow here for the day two live blog.
Note that slides from most presentations are now available at riscv.org.
Introduction: Rick O&amp;rsquo;Connor  This workshop has 325 attendees representing 101 companies and 25 universties. Largest outside of Silicon Valley. Rick gives the usual overview of the RISC-V Foundation structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC 0-5 milestone release</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/01/lowrisc-0-5-milestone-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 14:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2018/01/lowrisc-0-5-milestone-release/</guid>
      <description>The lowRISC 0.5 milestone release is now available. The various changes are best described in our accompanying documentation, but the main focus is the integration of open-source Ethernet IP. The tutorial demonstrates how to use Ethernet support to boot with an NFS root, as well as with a rootfs on SD card.
Our main development focus currently is migrating to a newer version of the upstream Rocket chip design and reintegrating our changes on top of that, but we felt that the integration of Ethernet support merits a release before that change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seventh RISC-V Workshop: Day Two</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/11/seventh-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 15:16:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/11/seventh-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</guid>
      <description>The seventh RISC-V workshop is concluding today at Western Digital in Milpitas. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Celerity: An Open Source 511-core RISC-V Tiered Accelerator Fabric: Michael Taylor  Built in only 9 months. Celerity is an accelerator-centric SoC with a tiered accelertor fabric. Implemented in TSMC 16nm FFC. 25mm2 die area, 385M transistors Why 511 RISC-V cores? 5 Linux-capable RV64G Rocket cores, 496-core RV32IM mesh tiled area &amp;ldquo;manycore&amp;rdquo;, 10-core RV32IM mesh tiled array (low voltage).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seventh RISC-V Workshop: Day One</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/11/seventh-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 15:16:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/11/seventh-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</guid>
      <description>The seventh RISC-V workshop is going on today and tomorrow at Western Digital in Milpitas. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Follow here for the day two live blog.
Introduction: Rick O&amp;rsquo;Connor  Workshop is sold out, 498 attendees registered representing 138 companies and 35 universities. There will be 47 sessions squeezed into 12 and 24 minute increments, plus 26 poster / demo sessions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GSoC 2017 student report: core lockstep for minion cores</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/10/gsoc-2017-student-report-core-lockstep-for-minion-cores/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 19:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/10/gsoc-2017-student-report-core-lockstep-for-minion-cores/</guid>
      <description>This year, as part of Google Summer of Code we had the pleasure of working with Nikitas Chronas. Alongside his degree studies, Nikitas had become involved with the Libre Space Foundation and developed a strong interest in the possibility of open source hardware in CubeSats. Fault tolerance of some sort is important for harsh environments, and Nikitas worked to add fault tolerance through the implementation of core lockstep for the PULPino-based minion core subsystem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving RISC-V LLVM forwards</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/moving-risc-v-llvm-forwards/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/moving-risc-v-llvm-forwards/</guid>
      <description>A high quality, upstream RISC-V backend for LLVM is perhaps the most frequently requested missing piece of the RISC-V software ecosystem. This blog post provides an update on the rapid progress we&amp;rsquo;ve been making towards that goal, outlines next steps and upcoming events, and tries to better explain the approach that we&amp;rsquo;re taking. As always, you can track status here and find the code here.
Status I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to make substantial progress since the last update.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC tagged memory OS enablement</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/lowrisc-tagged-memory-os-enablement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/lowrisc-tagged-memory-os-enablement/</guid>
      <description>This summer, we were fortunate enough to have Katherine Lim join the lowRISC team at the University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory as an intern. Katherine&amp;rsquo;s focus was on operating system and software enabled for lowRISC&amp;rsquo;s tagged memory, building upon our most recent milestone release. As Katherine&amp;rsquo;s detailed write-up demonstrates, it&amp;rsquo;s been a very productive summer.
The goal of this internship was to take the lowRISC hardware release, and demonstrate kernel support and software support for the hardware tagged memory primitives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We&#39;re hiring! Work on making open source hardware a reality</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/were-hiring-work-on-making-open-source-hardware-a-reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2017 08:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/were-hiring-work-on-making-open-source-hardware-a-reality/</guid>
      <description>We are looking for a talented hardware engineer to join the lowRISC team and help make our vision for an open source, secure, and flexible SoC a reality. Apply now!
lowRISC C.I.C. is a not-for-profit company that aims to demonstrate, promote and support the use of open-source hardware. The lowRISC project was established in 2014 with the aim of bringing the benefits of open-source to the hardware world. It is working to do this by producing a high quality, secure, open, and flexible System-on-Chip (SoC) platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building upstream RISC-V GCC&#43;binutils&#43;newlib: the quick and dirty way</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/building-upstream-risc-v-gccbinutilsnewlib-the-quick-and-dirty-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/09/building-upstream-risc-v-gccbinutilsnewlib-the-quick-and-dirty-way/</guid>
      <description>There are a number of available options for building a RISC-V GCC toolchain. You might use the build system from the riscv/riscv-tools repository, or investigate toolchain generators such as crosstool-ng. However in the case of riscv-tools, it&amp;rsquo;s not always clear how this corresponds to the code in the relevant upstream projects. When investigating a potential bug, you often just want to build the latest upstream code with as little fuss as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC 0-4 milestone release</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/06/lowrisc-0-4-milestone-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2017 12:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/06/lowrisc-0-4-milestone-release/</guid>
      <description>The lowRISC 0.4 milestone release is now available. The various changes are best described in our accompanying documentation, but in summary this release:
 Moves forward our support for tagged memory by re-integrating the tag cache, reducing overhead with a hierarchical scheme. This will significantly reduce caches misses caused by tagged memory accesses where tags are distributed sparsely. Integrates support for specifying and configuring tag propagation and exception behaviour. A PULPino based &amp;ldquo;minion core&amp;rdquo; has been integrated, and is used to provide peripherals such as the SD card interface, keyboard, and VGA tex display (when using the Nexys4 DDR FPGA development board).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apply now for GSoC 2017</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/03/apply-now-for-gsoc-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 09:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/03/apply-now-for-gsoc-2017/</guid>
      <description>We are very grateful for being selected again to take part as a mentoring organisation in the Google Summer of Code, now for the third year running. If you are a student who would like to be paid to work on open source during the summer, then take a look at the lowRISC ideas list and apply. The deadline for applications is 4pm UTC on April 3rd. We&amp;rsquo;re always very interested in ideas suggested by students, and encourage you to share them on our discussion list for feedback before making a proposal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 NetFPGA Design Challenge</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/02/2017-netfpga-design-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2017/02/2017-netfpga-design-challenge/</guid>
      <description>As most of you know, the majority of full-time development on lowRISC takes place at the University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory. However, we&amp;rsquo;re far from the only open source hardware activity at the University. Our colleagues on the NetFPGA project have an open source design challenge that many readers of this blog might be interested in. See the design challenge website, or read below for more details:
We are pleased to announce the 2017 NetFPGA Design Challenge!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC Q&#43;A</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/12/lowrisc-qa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/12/lowrisc-qa/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, lowRISC triggered a lot of discussion when someone submitted it to Hacker News. The comment thread became something of an impromptu Q+A about our project direction and status. I thought it was worth linking to it here and highlighting the discussion for a wider audience. If you have any additional questions, then feel free to comment on this blog post or else, as always, drop by our mailing list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fifth RISC-V Workshop: Day Two</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/11/fifth-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/11/fifth-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</guid>
      <description>Today is the second day of the fifth RISC-V workshop. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
OpenSoC System Architect: Farzad Fatollahi-Fard  Current architectures are wasteful. Only a small fraction of chip area goes to computation. For both GoblinCore and OpenHPC, ended up doing a lot of similar work to achieve only a point design. Why not make a generator to avoid repeating the same steps?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fifth RISC-V Workshop: Day One</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/11/fifth-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 15:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/11/fifth-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</guid>
      <description>The fifth RISC-V workshop is going on today and tomorrow at the Google&amp;rsquo;s Quad Campus in Mountain View. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Introduction: Rick O&amp;rsquo;Connor and Dom Rizzo  This workshop is yet again bigger than the last. 350+ attendees, 107 companies, 29 universities. The next workshop will be May 9th-10 in Shanghai, China.  RISC-V at UC San Diego: Michael Taylor  Startup software stacks today look a light like an iceberg.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating a Gantt chart from HJSON input</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/10/generating-a-gantt-chart-from-hjson-input/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/10/generating-a-gantt-chart-from-hjson-input/</guid>
      <description>This blog post is a slight departure from the normal topics here. Worry not, we&amp;rsquo;ll return to discussing Verilog, Chisel, and low-level software work soon. I wrote a quick script to help serve a need (producing a Gantt chart) and thought perhaps others would find it useful.
There are a wide range of online services to help produce and maintain Gantt charts, but none quite offered what I was looking for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC&#43;IMC internship: second update</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/07/lowriscimc-internship-second-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 14:23:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/07/lowriscimc-internship-second-update/</guid>
      <description>This is the second update from our team of interns, comprised of four University of Cambridge undergrads. Their work is kindly sponsored by IMC Financial Markets who are also helping to advise this summer project.
At the time of our last blog post, we had just finished VGA and were working on implementing the frame buffer. Over the last 2 weeks, we have made significant progress, completing the frame buffer and starting video decode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes from the fourth RISC-V workshop</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/07/notes-from-the-fourth-risc-v-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 16:08:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/07/notes-from-the-fourth-risc-v-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Many of the lowRISC team (Robert Mullins, Wei Song, and Alex Bradbury) have been in Boston this week for the fourth RISC-V workshop. By any measure, this has been a massive success with over 250 attendees representing 63 companies and 42 Universities. Wei presented our most recent work on integrating trace debug, which you&amp;rsquo;ll soon be able to read much more about here (it&amp;rsquo;s worth signing up to our announcement list if you want to be informed of each of our releases).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC / IMC internship week one - VGA output</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/07/lowrisc-/-imc-internship-week-one-vga-output/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 14:23:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/07/lowrisc-/-imc-internship-week-one-vga-output/</guid>
      <description>Begnning on Monday, June 27th, we had a team of four University of Cambridge undergrads begin a 10 week internship working on the lowRISC project at the Computer Laboratory, kindly sponsored by IMC Financial Markets (who are also helping to advise this project). The team will be blogging regularly over the course of the summer - I&amp;rsquo;ll pass over to them to introduce themselves.
After some initial brainstorming, we decided to aim to extend the current lowRISC SoC design to enable video output, with the final goal of playing video smoothly at a resolution of 640x480 on FPGA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing the LibreCores design contest and ORConf 2016</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/06/announcing-the-librecores-design-contest-and-orconf-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 15:39:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/06/announcing-the-librecores-design-contest-and-orconf-2016/</guid>
      <description>Our friends and collaborators at the Free and Open Source Silicon Foundation have launched the LibreCores design contest. This is a student design contest which aims to recognise and reward contributions to the open source hardware ecosystem. The main evaluation criteria are:
 Openness. Your work must be published under an established Open Source license. Reusability. How easily can your work be used and modified by someone else? Is it well documented?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC&#39;s 2016 Google Summer of Code Students</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/06/lowriscs-2016-google-summer-of-code-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 12:12:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/06/lowriscs-2016-google-summer-of-code-students/</guid>
      <description>The 2016 Google Summer of Code is now underway and we&amp;rsquo;re delighted to be working with five students, covering a variety of interesting projects. They have all introduced themselves over the past few weeks on our project mailing list. Many thanks to everyone who applied, to the mentors who volunteered, and to Google for sponsoring this programme. If your application was unsuccessful, I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll try again next year.
The projects for lowRISC in the 2016 GSoC are:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apply now to work with lowRISC in Google Summer of Code</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/03/apply-now-to-work-with-lowrisc-in-google-summer-of-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 20:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/03/apply-now-to-work-with-lowrisc-in-google-summer-of-code/</guid>
      <description>We are very grateful to have been selected to take part as a mentoring organisation in the Google Summer of Code for the second year running. As with last year, we&amp;rsquo;re working with a number of friends from across the wider open source hardware community to act as an umbrella for a range of hardware-related projects. If you are a student who would like to be paid to work on open source during the summer, then take a look at the lowRISC ideas list and apply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third RISC-V Workshop: Day Two</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/01/third-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 17:05:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/01/third-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</guid>
      <description>Today is the second day of the third RISC-V workshop. Again, I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day. See here for notes from the first day.
RISC-V ASIC and FPGA implementations: Richard Herveille  Look for freedom of design. Want to free migrate between FPGAs, structured ASICs, standard cell ASICs Want to make it easier to migrate FPGAs to ASICs for advantages in price, performance, power, IP protection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third RISC-V Workshop: Day One</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/01/third-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 17:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2016/01/third-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</guid>
      <description>The third RISC-V workshop is going on today and tomorrow at the Oracle Conference Center, California. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day. See here for notes from the second day.
Introductions and RISC-V Foundation Overview: Rick O&amp;rsquo;Connor  Save the date, the 4th RISC-V workshop will be July 12th-13th at the MIT CSAIL/Stata Center. In August 2015, articles of incorporation were filed to create a non-profit RISC-V Foundation to govern the ISA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Untethered lowRISC release</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/12/untethered-lowrisc-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/12/untethered-lowrisc-release/</guid>
      <description>Over the past several months, we&amp;rsquo;ve been working to provide a standalone or &amp;lsquo;untethered&amp;rsquo; SoC. Cores in the original Rocket chip rely on communicating with a companion processor via the host-target interface (HTIF) to access peripherals and I/O. This release removes this requirement, adding an I/O bus and instantiating FPGA peripherals. The accompanying tutorial, written by Wei Song, describes how to build this code release and explains the underlying structural changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC at ORConf 2015</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/08/lowrisc-at-orconf-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 10:51:14 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/08/lowrisc-at-orconf-2015/</guid>
      <description>Please join us October 9th-11th in Geneva, Switzerland for ORConf 2015. The event is kindly being hosted by CERN at the IdeaSquare. Last year&amp;rsquo;s ORConf was home to the first public talk on lowRISC and we&amp;rsquo;re delighted this year it will also be hosting a series of lowRISC and RISC-V discussions, serving as a European lowRISC and RISC-V workshop. ORConf has in recent years grown to cover a range of open source hardware topics beyond the original OpenRISC focus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second RISC-V Workshop: Day Two</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/06/second-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 17:00:45 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/06/second-risc-v-workshop-day-two/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the second day of the second RISC-V workshop today in Berkeley, California. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Z-scale. Tiny 32-bit RISC-V Systems: Yunsup Lee  Z-Scale is a family of tiny cores, similar in spirit to the ARM Cortex-M family. It integrates with the AHB-Lite interconnect. Contrast to Rocket (in-order cores, 64-bit, 32-bit, dual-issue options), and BOOM (a family of out-of-order cores).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second RISC-V Workshop: Day One</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/06/second-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 17:02:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/06/second-risc-v-workshop-day-one/</guid>
      <description>The second RISC-V workshop is going on today and tomorrow in Berkeley, California. I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping a semi-live blog of talks and announcements throughout the day.
Introductions and welcome: Krste Asanović  The beginning of Krste&amp;rsquo;s talk will be familiar for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s seen an introduction to RISC-V before. Pleasingly, there are a lot of new faces here at the workshop so the introduction of course makes a lot of sense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer of Code students for lowRISC</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/05/summer-of-code-students-for-lowrisc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 20:45:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/05/summer-of-code-students-for-lowrisc/</guid>
      <description>lowRISC was fortunate enough to be chosen as a mentoring organisation in this year&amp;rsquo;s Google Summer of Code. The Google Summer of Code program funds students to work on open source projects over the summer. We had 52 applications across the range of project ideas we&amp;rsquo;ve been advertising. As you can see from the range of project ideas, lowRISC is taking part as an umbrella organisation, working with a number of our friends in the wider open source software and hardware community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lowRISC tagged memory preview release</title>
      <link>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/04/lowrisc-tagged-memory-preview-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 22:28:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.lowrisc.org/blog/2015/04/lowrisc-tagged-memory-preview-release/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re pleased to announce the first lowRISC preview release, demonstrating support for tagged memory as described in our memo. Our ambition with lowRISC is to provide an open-source System-on-Chip platform for others to build on, along with low-cost development boards featuring a reference implementation. Although there&amp;rsquo;s more work to be done on the tagged memory implementation, now seemed a good time to document what we&amp;rsquo;ve done in order for the wider community to take a look.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>